[music]
>> Hello, I am Dr. Gaurav Dixit from Indian
Institute of Technology Roorkee. And
today we'll cover the introduction part
of the course a digital transformation
and technological innovation. This
particular course has been developed as
a core course
from the information systems discipline.
So let's understand what is information
systems. Now information systems is an
applied discipline of computer science
and engineering that draws from other
disciplines to save valuable information
products and services for target end
users. Now what are these you know
disciplines where you know it draws
from? So some of these reference
disciplines could be engineering,
mathematics, management science and
behavioral sciences. So the main idea in
information system is to learn from you
know the the research that is being
conducted in some of these reference
discipline and then use computer science
and engineering or information
technology in general to save a valuable
information products and services for
the benefit of target end users. Now
let's understand the research in the
information systems field. So mainly it
examines you know the technological
system or the social system but it also
can examine both technological system
and the social system side by side along
with it also investigate phenomena that
emerge from their interactions. That
means social system or the elements
within the social system interacting
with the elements of the technological
system. So, therefore, overall
technological system,
or both side-by-side simultaneous, you
know, analysis or examination or
research on it. And then most
importantly, the interactions between
these two system, technological system
and the social system. Now, what is the
main difference from parent discipline
that is computer science and engineering
and and the other reference disciplines
that
we just talked about the engineering,
the mathematics, management science, and
the behavioral sciences is that the
focus is on the emergent socio-technical
phenomena. Now, in terms of the research
audience, the scholars, you know, people
who work in information systems area,
what they are concerned with? So, the
scholars in general in any field, if
they are concerned with development,
use, and application of traditional,
new, and emerging information technology
to model representations of real-world
systems, then they would benefit from
what is happening in information systems
research. And you know, sometimes
because information technology is being
used to model representations of
real-world systems, these systems
sometimes are also referred to as
IT-based systems. So, the research
audience in general is the scholars who
are in any way concerned with the use of
information technology for real-life,
real-world problems
in general. Now, if we look at the
practical relevance in industrialized
world, the IT-based systems, they have
become ubiquitous. We see them, you
know, everywhere including this, you
know, the video lectures that we are
producing as part of NPTEL and SAM
courses. There also we see the
application of these you know, IT based
systems different aspects of the
production of these courses. Right? So,
IT based systems have become ubiquitous.
They have become They are important to
both whether we talk about the private
or the public sectors to individuals,
organizational, multinational and
transnational organizations. Whether we
talk about the organizations which are
you know, present in in a more
distributed format. They are present in
different countries or they have a more
centralized location in one country and
other locations they have a unit where
they are doing some of their work or
catering to that local market. Right?
So, IT based systems are involved in
everywhere. Right? So, we will see more
examples in the lecture for the same.
Now, if we look at you know, other areas
you know, different areas where IT based
systems are being used so they would
include a whole lot of areas but to name
a few agriculture, manufacturing,
services education you know, medicine,
defense, government. Now, as we already
you know, seeing in our day-to-day life
everything or most of the things
activities whether at home or at
workplace we are doing through our
smartphones interacting with the apps
and you know, going on with the task and
activities. So, all this is this comes
under purview of IT based systems and
overall under information systems. Now,
if we look for similar applied
disciplines just like as I said that
information systems being a you know,
sub-discipline or applied discipline of
computer science and engineering what
are other applied disciplines in other
fields. So, some of these are
bioinformatics. They also use you know,
a lot of analysis, data, IT systems, and
other things. Geographical information
systems, uh medical informatics, and
then accounting information systems,
which uh you know, accounting comes
uh under business umbrella, but there
there is so much of use of IT systems
that you know, you know, we refer to
that that that usage as accounting
information systems. Then there is a
neuro information systems, where
neuroscience uh you know, uh
applications on neurosciences research
using lot more, you know, information
systems, IT systems, and therefore this
uh area has emerged there as well. So,
these are some of the examples of you
know, applied disciplines, which are
similar to what you know, information
systems. Right? Now, having said all
this, then let's look at a definition of
information systems, which covers, you
know, some of the things that we have
talked till now. So, definition goes
like this. An information system is a
real-world system with human and machine
elements that process activities and
task using information technology,
relevant artifacts, and feedback loops
to save valuable information products
and services for target end users. So,
here you see that uh you know, we are
talking about a real-world system, which
is having both the human and machine
elements, and then uh you know, process
activities uh and task. Then we talk
about the information technology, the
other artifacts that might be part of
those activities and task, and uh you
know, you know, you know, in that
process, the information technology
might also be being used. And uh in
addition, the feedback loops. While
these human and machine elements are
there and in terms of completing the
activities or executing the activities
and task, uh there might be some
learnings from the shortcomings of the
overall, uh you know,
information system
at the human level or at the, you know,
machine level, the algorithm logic
level, or at output, input, or other
levels, right? So, some feedback loops
can be generated which can then be, you
know, worked upon to shape valuable,
uh you know, information products and
services and so that the end users, the
target end users,
uh you know, benefit from it.
Now, if we look at, uh examples of, uh
you know, information systems, then, you
know, first let's go through the some of
the software products for enterprise
users. So, first we'll focus on the
enterprise users and you can see that,
you know, first one is ERP. So, there
are a few examples that I have noted
down here.
Uh one product from SAP and then, you
know, Oracle NetSuite and then, in case
of SCM. So, ERP was enterprise resource
planning. So, that is a particular, you
know, category of enterprise system. And
then, uh the second one is SCM, that is
supply chain management system. And few
products in that category is SAP IPBP
and the Oracle, uh you know, SCM cloud.
And then, third category under this is,
uh CRM. So, that is customer
relationship management system, that is
another category of enterprise system.
So, one product that, uh you know, I
have noted down here is Salesforce CRM.
Then, uh next one is, uh you know,
business intelligence. That is another
category for enterprise system where,
you know, algorithms, uh whether it's
about machine learning, analytics, and
AI in general, they're being applied on
data so that some meaningful insights
are, you know, generated for, you know,
data-driven decision making. So, some
products that are listed here are
Microsoft Power BI and Tableau. So,
essentially these products mainly focus
on the visual analysis visualization
charts because this is BI
as such as an enterprise system is
mainly for consumption of managerial you
know executives right so therefore
more you know application of you know
visualization and descriptive and other
kinds of you know signals that are there
so these are some of the examples of
information systems software products
which are actually enterprise systems so
they target the enterprise users then
let's look at next category that is
software products for professional users
so
you know software engineers or other
professionals in different industries
the analyst business analyst you know
data engineers data scientists there
so many
professionals across different
industries and they might benefit from
you know some of these very generic
products like Microsoft co-pilot which
is like you know new thing where you can
use generative AI to you know help in
the task activities that you are
doing and then the Microsoft Office the
traditional you know software product
which most of us use to you know create
documents and create slides
presentations and many other things
right so these this particular category
is for the professional user then there
are software products for conferencing
and meeting so Microsoft Teams you know
Zoom workplace so these are some of the
examples of the products so what they
facilitate they facilitate
you know meetings
people working or collaborating on a
project they can meet share create
meeting notes using some generative AI
app and all that so these products
you know
another example for this category then
in case of e-commerce we have Adobe
Commerce or, you know, earlier Magento.
So, this is another category. So, in
case, you know, you are into e-commerce,
you know, industry, then some of the
companies might be using Adobe Commerce,
Magento, this product to run their
websites and the back end and many other
things that go with it. So, this is
another example of information system in
case of,
you know, e-commerce. And the next one
is software products for email. So, this
is something that is most of all most
organizations they have sort of adopted
email as their main communication tool.
So, there are also two products that are
listed, Gmail, Google Workspace, and the
Zimbra, the open source option that we
have for, you know, email. So, that is
also there.
All right. So, under email category,
these two examples which can be
considered as information systems. Then
internet platforms. Internet platforms
for social networks.
Now, there are so many people who log in
to these social networking websites,
create accounts, interact with people or
the content or whatever they want to
follow. So, this also becomes an example
of information systems. So, some of
these, you know, platforms are LinkedIn,
X, and Facebook. So, you would notice
that, you know, the previous few
examples, I was using the term software
products, you know, both in case of
enterprise and the software and other
categories, enterprise and the
professional and other categories. And
here, I've started using the term
internet platforms, not software
products, because some of these, you
know, apps actually act like a platforms
with network effect that will be, you
know, discussing later in this course.
Right? So, here you would see different
sites are connected to, you know, some
of these platforms and we'll understand
their interactions and some of the
concepts related to that later. So, this
category internet platforms for social
network, this is another example of an
information system. Then, next is
internet platforms for payments. All
right. So, now for everything we are
making, you know, digital transactions,
digital payments. So, let's see a few of
the categories here. Digital wallets or
real-time, you know, payments. We have
some of these apps, PhonePe, Google Pay,
these being the main, you know, leaders
in Indian market. And then, if you are a
credit card or debit card user, then
Visa and MasterCard, you know, these are
the two platform
which facilitate the transactions, you
know, for the
among cards which are, you know, in
compliance with Visa and MasterCard, you
know, platform. Then, there is gateways,
payment gateways. So, there are two
names that are that I've noted down
here, Razorpay and PayPal. So, these are
two examples of internet platforms in
case of gateways, payment gateways.
Right. So, these are some of the
examples,
internet platforms for payments, which
will also which can also be considered
as, you know, information systems. Then,
you know, next set of examples are like
these, internet platforms for
publishing. So, all of us nowadays we
prefer to read from PDFs using our
tablets, smartphones, notebooks, which
are more, you know, mobile devices in a
way, more portable. So, some of the
examples are, you know, Amazon Kindle
Direct Publishing. So, this is for
books. And then, in case of scientific
arti- articles, we have, you know,
Elsevier, Springer Nature. So, these are
a few examples. So, these can also be
considered as, you know, examples of
information systems. Right. So, these
were the internet platforms for
publishing. Next step is the internet
platforms for streaming. Right. So, what
are the examples in this category? So,
in case of video streaming,
I've noted down Netflix, YouTube,
TikTok. So, these are examples of, you
know, information systems which are sort
of platforms, internet platforms for
streaming
video first up, then music. Under music,
we have a Spotify, Apple Music, right?
So, uh
these are the two companies, these are
the two apps which sort of dominate most
of the market share in digital music
category.
Right? So, these can also be considered
important examples of internet platforms
for streaming and can be considered, you
know, examples of information systems.
Then, few more uh examples of
information system new categories, uh
internet platforms for news, right? So,
we have, you know, in in few years, we
have transitioned from, you know,
acquiring or getting our or receiving
our news from TV channels to printed
newspapers uh
to we have shifted to online news,
internet news. So, what are the
examples? So, under general category, we
have, you know, some of these popular,
you know, news websites, news portals,
BBC, CNN, TOI, NDTV and all that. So,
these can also be uh you know,
considered as example of information
systems under the category internet
platforms for news. Similarly, the next
step is, you know, internet platforms
for booking. So, uh in this category, uh
you know, we whenever we make our travel
arrangements, travel plans, so nowadays
everything we do uh via internet, via
these apps. So, under flight and hotel
category, we have, you know, some
examples like Agoda, Booking.com,
Skyscanner. Some of these uh you know,
websites web portals uh you know, I've
noted down here and these are also
examples of, you you information systems
and under the category internet
platforms for booking. Similarly, in
case of movie or some event that we want
to book or that we want to go for. So,
BookMyShow, Paytm, so these are some
Indian, you know, examples in this
category. Now, moving on to next, uh,
you know, example category that is, you
know, internet platforms for shopping or
ordering. So, in this case, you know,
four categories placed them two. So,
first one is general. So, we have
generic e-commerce websites, you know,
Amazon and Flipkart. So, where we, you
know, shop or order for certain items.
And then there is another category,
fashion. I've noted down Myntra. Then
food. I've noted down Zomato, Swiggy.
Then we have, you know, delivery.
Uh, there I've noted on Blinkit and
Instamart. So, these are some of the,
you know, apps, uh, which act like
internet platforms for shopping,
ordering. And these can be considered as
an examples of, uh, you know, uh,
information systems. Moving on to, uh,
the next category that is internet
platforms for, you know, advertising.
So, here I've noted down few. For
example, Google Ads, Meta Ads, and also
Amazon Ads, right? So, this pretty much
covers the whole, most of the options or
more dominant options, so to say, in
case of digital marketing and and and
including, uh, you know, social media
marketing. Right? So, now many companies
they prefer to advertise, you know,
their their ad on on on digital
platforms. So, these are some of the
platforms which facilitate that. And
they can also be considered as examples
of information systems. Then moving on
to the next category that is internet
platforms for travel. Now, in this case,
if we just take the, uh, you know,
subcategory for taxi, then Uber and Ola,
these are two examples of the apps which
can be considered information systems
under this category internet platforms
for travel. So, let's you know, move on
to the next you know, category that is
cloud services. So, all of us for our
file sharing we use you know, Google
Drive or OneDrive, right? Some of these
popular you know, platforms, right? So,
this category is there cloud services
for hosting apps, right? So, here what
are the examples? So, this one is mean
mainly for businesses where you know, if
you are running a business and you want
to host an app, then cloud services
being provided by these vendors Amazon
Web Services that is from Amazon,
Microsoft Azure from Microsoft and
Google Cloud Platform GCP from Google.
So, these three vendors cloud vendors
Amazon, Microsoft and Google, you know,
their cloud services where you know,
they are facilitating businesses to host
their apps. They can also be considered
an example of information systems
because we can clearly you know, observe
that you know, the interaction between
the business or the IT team of the
business interacting with the you know,
cloud services being provided by these
vendors and then they decide what kind
of software they want to you know, host
there in the cloud or what you know,
what they will do with their data, what
kind of interaction, how many users will
log on to it, whether they'll open it to
the customers or whether this is only
for the internal consumption, right? So,
all these in you know, interaction
points come up, right? So, that emergent
socio-technical phenomena comes up,
right? So, this is another example of
you know,
information systems cloud services for
hosting apps. Then moving on to now we
earlier talked about the software
products which were for the enterprise
then you know, for the professional then
we moved on to internet platforms.
Many of them we use for our day-to-day
uses. Then we are moving to the AI
systems. Right? Now, first category
under this is AI systems for
forecasting. Now, here in the two
subcategories I have noted down. First
is finance. So, if you want to forecast
stock prices, because you might be
making your, you know, investment
decision. You want to buy some stock,
sell some stocks. So, the AI system that
is giving you that input, that
decision-making input, whether a, you
know, set of stocks or a particular
stock or the stock that you are
interested in, whether it will go up or
down the next day or next week or next
month. So, those inputs you are
incorporating your decision making. And
therefore, the whole interaction,
whether it's about the machine element
or the human element and the interaction
and the feedback loop, put together all
this, uh, we can consider as an
information system. So, under finance
category, we can note down stock prices,
then market volatility could be another
example. Then others can be, you know,
product demand. We can have an AI system
for product demand, because that might
be connected to our, you know, inventory
management and other production planning
and all those aspects. Then energy
consumption. So, for the energy, you
know, producing, uh, companies or
distributing companies, you know, to to
ability, you know, using AI system to be
able to, you know, forecast energy
consumption can be beneficial, because
then they can plan their operations
accordingly. Next category here is AI
systems, uh, for you know, internet
platform. So, internet platforms we
earlier talked about and we consider,
you know, those platforms as such, uh,
you know, information systems. But AI
systems for those platforms, uh, is
another example for, you know,
information system, because, uh, they
can also benefit from AI. For example,
you know, recommended systems for
personalization. So, we see many of
these apps, whether it is YouTube or
Netflix,
uh, when we are watching, uh, you know,
when we have sufficient history of
watching certain items, then these
platforms, whether YouTube or Netflix,
they start recommending, you know, some
items to us. So, the system, the AI
system that is doing that is referred to
as recommender systems. So, this can
also be considered as an example of
information systems, which is actually
and under the category of AI systems for
internet platforms. Then, the next one
is, you know, link prediction. Link
prediction for, you know, social
networking or search, right? So,
whenever we log into the system and, you
know, we go to Google search or any
other search engine, and we have certain
information that we are looking for, and
we enter our, you know, query terms, and
then we go to another
scenario is that we log into the social
networking websites, and we look to
connect to our friends, right? So, in
both the these cases, you know, AI
system which is about predicting link,
who could be What could be the
meaningful links that can give you the
information that you are looking for,
and that or that can connect you to the
friends that you are looking for. So,
these are This is another example for,
you know, AI systems for internet
platforms. Next is,
uh, AI systems for, you know,
communication or interaction, right? So,
now most of us are, you know, totally
taken by
the hype that is around the large
language models, the generative AI and
everything. Now, there are already some
successful platforms running like
ChatGPT, and Gemini, Google Assistant,
many others, Perplexity, Perplexity,
right? So, some of these examples I've
noted down here. So, conversational
search Q&A AI systems which are
facilitating conversational search
Q&A. So, these are some of the
products are Google Gemini, Perplexity.
So, these are some examples where user
comes up with their own query that, you
know, the detail that they are looking
for the answer that they are looking for
or the conversation that they're looking
for. They enter that query and the that
particular, you know, platform, whether
it's Google Gemini or Perplexity, uh the
AI system that responds back, you know,
with a response, right? So, the whole
interaction that is happening there and
the
you know, overall setup. Uh considering
that we, you know, this can also be
considered as an example of information
system. Then virtual assistant general
category Google Assistant, which we can
use to control certain things, to make
calls and other things using mobile
phones. Similarly, another category is
subcategory is virtual assistant for
music, for example, Amazon Alexa that we
interact with if you want to play a
music. So, here a human interacting with
an AI system to play certain content,
certain music or some other things or
get answer to a particular query, right?
So, therefore, the overall human-machine
element and the feedback loop, the
corrections, improvements,
uh all that put together and the
interactions and the emergent
uh socio-technical phenomena that is
there, we can consider this as an
example of information system. Then in
case of social media, we have Grok AI.
So, that is another example where Grok
has access to all the data, all the, you
know, tweets that are there in the
platform X and whenever, you know, we
have a query about some political
situation or sports or any other topic
of interest, uh it is able to gather
sufficient, you know, uh you know, feed
that is there already there in the in
the X platform and then in general in
internet and able to come up with a
response. So, this is an example of, you
know, users interacting with a, you
know, AI system which is hosting hosted
on a social media platform X. And then
again, sometimes you don't get the, you
know, the response
as per your expectation or as per, you
know,
your expectation in terms of accuracy
and other aspects, other metrics, then
you again revise your question and that
whole interaction creates this an
example of another information system.
Moving on, now having
gone through so many things from
software products to internet platforms
to AI systems, so therefore all aspects
of our life, whether we talk about the
enterprise context or the professional
context or our personal context, we are
touched by these, you know, IT-based
systems or in general, we are touched by
these information systems where
human-machine interactions are happening
and the socio-technical phenomena is
emerging. So, all this is happening day
in day out and this all this comes under
the purview of information systems area.
So, then there are so many options for
conducting research. So, what are the
directions for innovation information
systems? So, we can, you know, take
various angles to it. So, I have
created, you know, few, you know,
categories here. You know, first up, we
can take the customer angle. So, from
the customer angle, what are the, you
know, directions that we can take for
innovation or research? So, handling the
different needs of existing customers.
So, whether we can, you know, using, you
know, information systems and the data
that is coming there and the feedback
loops that are there, can we take
advantage of all that human-machine
interaction, the data, the feedback loop
and use that to understand whether there
are any different needs for existing
customers. And that's how we can improve
our,
you know, the current state of, you
know, the overall information systems or
a particular component of it. Maybe just
the machine, maybe just the algorithm or
maybe the human
interaction or the interface
that is there, or maybe some other
aspect in terms of output or the input.
We can make changes to the input or the
output or other aspects to it. Then,
solving new customers' needs. This is
another angle.
Uh whether the existing information
system it is catering to all kinds of
customer or whether there are some
customers which are which have, you
know, not, you know, interacted with the
platform, interacted with the
information systems, or the systems that
are part of it. Then, whether, you know,
we can take this angle for innovation,
for research, whether we can solve needs
of these new customers so that they can
also become part of our, you know,
ecosystem, or they can also become part,
you know, one of target end users for
our information system. Then, moving on
from a product and service angle. So,
from a product and service angle, what
could be the,
you know, angle for innovation or angle
for research here? We can improve the
current state of information products
and services. So, when I say current
state in the sense, you know, whether
the AI system,
you know, different versions of ChatGPT
has come. So, that is a continuous
improvement, right? So, OpenAI teams
keeps coming up with a new, you know,
stable release, new versions of ChatGPT.
So, that is what is being referred to at
referred to at here
that, you know, improving the current
state. Similarly for other AI system,
similarly for other internet platforms,
whether it is social media platforms,
Facebook or X, or whether it is search
engine. So, scope of improvement is
there, and whether current state can be
improved. So, that can be another angle
for innovation or research.
Now, moving on
to a few other, you know, directions for
innovation. The process from process and
activity angle. So, can we change some
of the characteristics that are
linked to these information systems? For
example, the structure, integration
level, complexity, you know, the
patterns, the exception handling that is
happening. Maybe some of the exceptions
are not being handled by the current
state of information systems or the
machine element of it, right? Or the
human element of it. So, whether we can,
you know, change some of those
characteristics, whether the structure
is, you know, quite complex, whether we
can simplify it, right? Whether we can
simplify the, you know, AI system that
is within it that is powering the
overall that is giving the machine part
to an information system. So, whether we
can improve that. Integration with, you
know, different sources, all right?
Whether the input is input might be
coming from, you know, a limited set of
sources, whether we can expand on it or
whether we can connect to other
information systems, all right? So, that
is there. Then the complexity, whether
users users find it easy to interact
with that information system. So, all
these process and activity angles are
there. The patterns, the exception
handling and all that. Then the within
this category itself, there are other
things that we can change. For example,
we can change details.
For example, adding, removing, or, you
know, combining steps
so that the overall information systems
improve or, you know, we can, you know,
change execution execution procedures
for specific steps. So, all these are,
you know, some of the research
directions or some of the research
angles or innovation angles that are
there, you know, from the process and
activity angle. Moving on. Now, from the
human participant angle, because one
side of it is human. So, it is all the
whole, uh, uh, you know, information
system one important part here is
human-machine interaction that is
happening as we talked about. So, uh,
whether we can take the human
participant angle,
uh, which is actually very common uh,
research angle in in business context,
and in, you know, AI context or, you
know, information technology context,
the focus uh, shifts more on the
technical element or the machine
element. While in the business context,
focus tends to shift on the human
uh, you know,
uh, you know, element. And in between
the human-machine interaction, the most
interesting part, some of the
researchers focus on that also. So, if
we look at the human participant angle,
you know, training angle, whether
training for new skills are needed,
whether, you know, uh, the professionals
in an organization whether they needed
training to be able to work with agentic
AI or, you know, LLMs in general, right?
Or any other technology, for example,
blockchain or, you know, any other edge
computing for that matter. Changing
incentives because one hurdle could be
if human part of the information system,
if they are not able to interact
sufficiently well, uh, within an
information system, then they might not
be there might not be meaningful output,
the meaningful information products and
services that we can generate out of the
information systems. So, therefore, uh,
whether changing incentives sometimes
work, uh, even with a, you know, you
know, information system which had
issues with it, but if you change the
incentives, then people are able to
figure out, uh, ways around, and they
are able to interact with it, and they
are able to, uh, come up with, uh,
meaningful, uh, you know, output in
terms of information products and
services. So, this is another angle. And
changing social aspects, whether the
culture, whether the other, you know,
rules, norms, managerial support, other
things, whether they can, you know, help
in terms of, you know, improving the
overall benefit that we are extracting
from information systems. So, all these
angles are there, you know, idea is to
either, you know, improve the adoption
or the diffusion or improve the output,
some element of it where, you know,
human's, you know, perspective is also
accounted for. So, uh till now, let's do
a quick recap of what we have discussed
till now. So, we have discussed, you
know, what is information systems, the
field of it, and uh you know, the
definition of information systems, the
similar disciplines. We also talked
about different examples of lots of
examples of information systems starting
from the software products to internet
platforms to AI systems. Then, uh you
know, we started our discussion on what
are the some of the research directions
that people undertake for innovation,
you know, in information systems. So,
you know, let's stop here. We'll
continue in the next uh session. Thank
you.
>> [music]
[music]